this computer yes well Pamela thank you
so much from for making time for this
conversation it's if for me it's really
already been a lovely learning journey
to have this conversation series that I
seem to be doing I'm surprised that's
what's what's emerging and I'm calling
it the regeneration rising and
conversations about regenerative
practice and I already had a really nice
conversation with Jason twill that and
Dominique Hesse and dropped in on she
couldn't make that the whole the whole
call and we were talking a lot about the
connections between both Australian and
Maori indigenous wisdom and how they
actually see resonance with the the kind
of thinking and the intention M that is
in in regenerative practice and how they
can mutually fertilize each other those
those wisdom traditions to some extent
and and I also like I Jason really
deeply opened up with a personal story
so I went at yesterday talked to Bill I
also asked him to really start with if
if regenerative practice is
fundamentally different from all these
other practices because it really
acknowledges that the work really starts
within and that ultimately it's about
shifting consciousness ways of seeing
the way that we ask questions and
observe ourselves in how we even frame
how to respond to the question how we
can add value and and regenerate a place
and I would love to hear how you got
into all of this and what was the
stories what were the moments where you
just felt called to do this kind of work
and and then inform yourself on how to
do it so well specifying moments is
always interesting I may be just in let
me start with a more general statement I
kind of popped into life as as I think
from early days a very strong advocate
proselytizer sort of personality
so a lot of my life early life in school
and college and and in the few years
afterwards were filled with peace
movement with civil rights I mean I was
out there sure that that we were going
to transform the world and do it next
week if we could just think and push
hard enough and that was a lot of you
know I was out organizing things that
Stanford the around the Vietnam War in
1962 and nobody even heard of it at that
point in you know our area but that kind
of carried me forward that was I didn't
felt it was really important to be
responsible and take a role and then I
got one of those sort of up the side
that had events and our daughter got
cancer and she was bone cancer she was
11 when that happened and she was truly
one of these old Souls just quite
remarkable human being
and we traveled that journey with her
for three years and one of the things
that I learned that she helped teach me
and many other people was how ephemeral
the kind of functional things we do and
successes we see and how exterior they
are to what and who we really need to be
and so during the time I'd been working
with Carol Sanford I mean we were our
daughters met when they were two years
old and were best friends and so that's
what sort of started that relationship
and so Carol and I had been working on a
number of things she had started going
to Charlie Crohn's sessions and working
with that group and so she'd bring back
and talk about what she's doing and I'd
go out and bring it into my practice and
so I've started it was
all this was while dealing with the
family and Jessica and supporting her
and so it was in the background hovering
but not the central focus so the thing
that I got out of that was there there's
a saying that that kerchief who's sort
of one of the key people in fourth way
work which was part of the lineage of
this work is man cannot do and I didn't
really ever understand that until that
experience and I thought sitting there
with with her I cannot do but I can be
and become something that can make a
difference but I don't know this reminds
me of the one of my favorite go chief
quotes is we have to stop thinking of
ourselves as beings that do and have to
start thinking of ourselves as doings
that be and that's exactly Matthew Fox
is a similar statement he said we should
call ourselves human doings because of
the way we focus yeah so I the month a
couple of weeks after Jessica died I
went for the first time to actually sit
in and with Charlie sessions and so it
was it one of the things that it did for
me was coming in in that place and
stayed was to be really present with not
the functional knowledge things that
were going on in the session but the
energy and the quality of energy and
being that was present took on a
tangibility for me but I had never
really experienced before so that was my
entry to this work and a lot of people
when we talk about what we're working on
is shifting thinking to him to think of
it as an intellectual process and it's
always challenging to people to say and
as an intellectual process
is doesn't have heart it's abstract and
it's it's a challenge to for people to
get over that because we are so firmly
taught in Western culture the thinking
is about in intellectual exercise it's a
functional actually a functional process
so that's that's how I got involved and
it was it it gave me time to sort of
really I think the question I was asking
us what kind of instrument do I need to
be hmm and it took you know a couple of
years to figure that out I worked with
because the the Institute was focused
around business that was the way to get
involved I'd always been in social
causes
community organizing and so on and this
shifted I learned an enormous amount as
a result of working in business behind a
serious I could say Mia and good could
you say a little bit mom as if this was
the Institute that Johnny Kron ran over
like yeah Johnny clone sessions if the
there was something called the network
which was a network of consultants who
worked and learned together from a
particular lineage and Charlie was
probably there were three three folks
who were kind of cord of formation of
that and they they were the roles they
described for themselves had to do with
right being right action and right
knowledge as opposed to hierarchy and
Charlie's role was right knowledge and
that really was appropriate because it's
that was his work I mean it's just it
was continually weaving together
multiple
lineages some very ancient some more
recent david bohm to to the sufis to
kerchief and john bennett systematics
was a very big part of it but his it was
right knowledge in the sense of knowing
not a thing known but the process of
knowing I think that's a really critical
distinction to make is I think it's one
of the reasons why this is this work
feels more resident to indigenous people
is that this the understanding of
knowledge is knowing a process this
continuing going is very much more akin
than the Western sense of knowledge is
it's a known just fascinating because we
bill and I spoke about this yesterday
that this work is dynamic so on the one
hand it is completely built on a deep
lineage of these people and and then
it's constantly evolving so it's not a
kind of going back to Bennett M in that
sense but always being informed and
inspired and and revisiting these
frameworks to then bring them into into
a even more appropriate application in
right now right here I think the key
word in there and what you just said
Daniel is evolving because we have a
tendency in the West to sort of take run
into some wall or difficulty and say ok
this doesn't work anymore we'll find
something else or we want to find our
own distinctive place and so we give it
a new name
and say this is much better I am that
we're doing this with sustainability now
it's interesting to see you know it's
suddenly the sustainability isn't good
enough it's a failure it's not far
enough and nobody seems to be asking
well maybe we didn't really understand
what sustainability meant in the sense
of a living world
so evolving it you know if you look at
the sciences Einstein
science far away from Newton but he
encompassed he didn't negate what Newton
found he encompassed it in a larger
picture of understanding and bomb did
the same thing so I'd like to think that
what's happening with this work is that
as it evolves its encompassing in a
larger understanding and deeper
understanding not changing that but it
requires really understanding what's a
very worthy it's it's sort of this
dynamic like what comes to mind is the
spiral yeah and like just I mean in in
Wilbur's frame it will be called
transcend and include rather than
transcend and exclude to build on it and
and also what when you think of it as a
developmental pathway as an evolutionary
pathway the entire pathway has to be
available to people on the learning
journey on their personal development
journey in order for them to find the
entry point where they're at and so in
that sense it is dynamic and it's
co-present but but there's always an
evolving edge and that it pushes it it's
a guy and I think not just a spiral but
it's actually moving and encompassing
more as it moves up yeah I think that's
exactly right and it I've really come to
appreciate the importance of
understanding something which is
different from no knowledge about it
before I try to evolve or build on it or
extend it in some way
you know in in many ways what for us
evolution is about is it's an and
regeneration is if we don't understand
what's at the core essence of something
and we try to improve it we end up
imposing a pattern we're bringing in
from somewhere else when we see this has
happened over and over again in Western
colonial times in science in business in
the way we plan cities we with the best
of intentions
we are looking to improve but we don't
truly understand what's at the core
heart that makes something who and what
it is and that's that's at the very very
heart of what what we are working within
in this particular cosmology and
ontology and technology that makes up
what we're doing I find I find it
fascinating to me personally on two
levels because on the one hand it's it's
the working with the potential rather
than the problem working with the like
really being placed sourced and and
working with the knowledge that whatever
you do in any place no matter how small
or how large if you like working by
originally its core present with the
whole world
so you actually the local world is also
a global work but then at the same time
as you were saying that I was sort of
tugging on my own master it was landing
in me also with them since that with
regard to that long lineage that you're
just describing what madness has been
nurtured by people I Charlie crow knew
Carroll and and people in Regenesis I
absolutely and joyfully am a humble
apprentice still learning the depth of
that frame and and and I guess my my
excitement about wanting to have a
conversation before I maybe even fully
deeply understand it um to the depth of
it is that it's so strongly resonates
with the two other main influences in in
my own thinking and because and it has a
each connection because because Henry
bought oft and his wonderful book agar
Thien the wholeness of nature agar Thien
way of science and this almost
phenomenological approach that Gerda
brought in that was reminding us to stay
present with how we bring the world into
being how our organizing ideas actually
shape what we think is out there but
it's not we've created it by the way we
enter with in relation with it and that
was really really influential for me
when I was at Omaha college in 2001-2002
and I worked with Henry directly and
then about 10 years later I know X 7
days later actually I I was infant horn
running a unit hog workshop on I think
it was Zero Carbon housing and and
sustainability in the built environment
or something and somebody signed up and
an Ellis my wife who at the time was the
secretary for this unit our training
center that I was working with said
check out the website of this person
who's just signed up there called
decision integrity they're down in
Pitlochry and and I think you'll like
the website so I looked at the website
and it was Tony Hudson's website and
Tony is in the IFF that he later invited
me into the international futures for
him and the connection here is that Tony
was in JG Bennett's research lab the
head of research and Henry who was
Baum's PhD student at the back college
came and worked at Con Springs as well
and so both of them in very different
ways and Tony with his world systems map
that you can see behind me there and
with with the work with three horizons
and all the frameworks that are curated
within a ch3 Union and the international
futures forum gave me so much and then
Henry with this particular attention to
our way of seeing being so central and
that that's why I'm so excited and maybe
a little bit too full of energy to
explore where these
things can meet um yeah no they do and I
mean phenomenology is is another core to
this work and it's I mean I know one of
the things that we when we were working
on developing Regenesis Charlie was and
bringing it into all of the sessions
that we folks were involved in with him
he started using that to be able to
bring people who were much not in that
world much more business oriented into
beginning to experience things from that
level more explicitly and it's the the
term we use often when we talk about
storing place and trying to first be the
experience the essence in core what's
that what's the core patterns of the
place is to be step in and walk around
and be conscious of how that place is
processing us you're literally being
processed all the time by the places
it's another way of saying and this was
Charlie's phrase that he was using with
the group who was working with the
vineyard a bio dynamic vineyard one of
the first ones they were trying to set
up and he was used that phrases said
just walk around and observe how its
processing you now that takes
consciousness of what's going on inside
of us and that's that's one of the
things I actually would like to talk
about Daniel because I think there's
there's a lot of exciting and wonderful
things being written now shared
disseminated with everywhere around
things like regenerative agriculture
regenerative economies and so on it's a
really optimistic and powerful and
hopeful time and in all of that
happening so it one of the things that's
that we've been doing is sort of saying
okay this is great because when we
started regeneration had to do with
biology that you couldn't find it
anywhere else or regenerative brakes
maybe
in the 90s it was such an obscure sort
of thing so it's it feels you know it's
finally now taking its place so what is
our role and the role of our work in
this now grew vastly quickly expanding
ecosystem where can we uniquely
contribute value in it and it's an
ongoing dialogue with us as part of how
we work on continuing to evolve what we
can bring and as I look it out and read
the thing one of the things that keeps
coming to me is is something you you
referred to as sort of self development
or personal development and I think
people don't have when they hear those
terms they they hear them through the
filter of the way we normally think
about things like personal development
or self development and so I want to
just address that a little bit because I
think that's one of the things that we
do that's and have developed a way of
enabling people to work that's
distinctive to this they say sort of
starts with the reality that we as
humans existent in essentially two
worlds you could say okay so we've got
an intrinsic world we live in an
extrinsic world and they're always both
at the same time and the intrinsic world
is all about it's an inner world of and
it's kind of the mental processing that
goes on in that if we're aware of it is
sort of signals to us who we want to be
what's going on how how we want to
behave in a situation so on most of the
time we're not even aware of that mental
processing most of our thinking is about
the extrinsic which is what to do about
the world up there what we should be
doing in relationship to it the the
issue then becomes when we are
unconscious of the intrinsic processing
which is developing how we respond and
engage with the world and we don't even
see that and we're only looking at the
outside we tend to become reactive
beings it's and lead that's what leads
to this so emphasis on doing because
we're not in Jesus so one of the the
core pieces in this work when we work we
call it actually is the developmental
process but we're always working on
actualization and realization working on
being able to manifest new effectiveness
and capabilities while realizing greater
potential and never separating those two
because that's at the core of that guy
you were talking about so the the
challenge is how do we become conscious
in the moment of how we are processing
our world and processing our thinking in
ourselves wouldn't you say that that is
at the core of personal development like
ultimately they like even the
conventional understanding of personal
development is is leading up to that
point where you can feel a reaction
rising and then you can reflect on how
your own filters and your own triggers
have produced that action before you
then respond to the situation I think
it's at the core when it is really truly
self actualizing but most of the
practices for working on that are all
are about going off and into a retreat
or meditation or what all in all of
those are really valuable and important
processes I don't want to theirs they
they all have a role at different times
in places what we work on is how do you
actually do use life moment by moment as
a school for working on that in oneself
and so it requires more will and
discipline to be able to do that but if
we're really going to involve who we are
and our being we have to do it while
we're working
and so a lot of the practices and the
frameworks that we use are and and the
kind of working together to support each
other to be friends in the work this is
about bringing that into a a meeting at
work a presentation to a client it's
like how can I bring that consciousness
of the inner processes and how it's
affecting the outer and bring them into
harmony in while I'm striving to
actually do something significant and it
certainly is bolstered by meditation
practices and by retreat practices but
ultimately that's where it's got to be
be brought to bear if we're really gonna
make the change that from doing be human
doings to human beings I'm curious
whether like because as as you were
speaking about this with regard to how
you function internally as a team within
within Regenesis and when you do the
work as a community and I somehow had
this yes fire
I always fire his work I I was briefly
reminded me of the kind of rite of
passage work of Vision Quest work I've
done and the importance of when you come
back from the mountain and you tell your
story and of the process of mirroring of
having somebody else reflect what you
that the story you tell back to you
is there any practice that you've
developed in the team that that when you
when you like how to gently remind
somebody to take that second second
level observation of the own practice
observation you remember you come in
contact with but one of the
sort of core frameworks we introduced at
the beginning of TRT is three lines of
work yeah of course yeah so the if first
line work is about developing the self
to be able to be to fully realize one's
potential and I that's another word
that's kind of a soft that gets pretty
flabby but if you sort of think of
potential as the gap between what I am
now and what I could be if I was fully
pursuing and realizing my purpose which
means a contribution to something larger
so that would be what the actualization
of if that first line work is a second
line work I'm taking on stewardship for
supporting those I'm working with to
also be on that path but always in
relationship to our collective aim of
contributing to something larger and in
in the world so that's where we get that
sort of in a sense it's moving up
scaling but it's different from nested
wholes it's not the same thing it's that
but it's the way we work together and so
there's a whole number of practices part
of it is if you to move a team that's
one of the things we're trying to do
through TRP and through the regenerative
practitioner of course is having study
cohorts and we'll be bringing the same
thing encouraging it as we start the
co-learning Network next this year is to
give people the the support in
structuring second line work groups in a
sense even though it may not be in your
your own team or business but it can
lead to that ideally it is but it's
where you have friends and the work who
gather together - who have a similar
understanding and not necessarily all it
affects better if they're not all at the
same level you always want to sort it's
like learning tennis you want to
practice with somebody better than you
but you also
by helping along somebody who's
resourcing somebody who's coming along
behind so having those kinds of groups
where people are working on their first
and third line but getting support for
building the consciousness in from from
folks who can remind you of ways to work
together to do that you know we just
little things I'll get an example from a
course we ran in Vancouver but this last
fall we want one of the sort of little
mantras is that in this work is to start
from potential not but not problems the
problems were starting from what's in
the past and by we had a two-day retreat
at the end of the course and by the end
of it people were in and these were
people who just met some of them were
from the same company but some of them
had just met at the beginning of this
two and a half months they were with the
listening to somebody reporting out and
say okay David you're solving a problem
again and they had permission to do that
because they were co-learning yeah I
think that's the key thing it's about
I'm inviting you in to my development
and I invite you with the understanding
that we have a similar practice and
respect for each other but I'm inviting
you to be a friend in the workbook to me
and I'm welcome being reminded I don't
want feedback I want to just have
something that just sort of wakes me up
a little bit and makes me be conscious
again of what I'm how I'm processing
myself and in this context how would you
do that sometimes and notice that there
is such a specificity of language that
then also in order to very clearly say
one thing okay it's in the language
structure you then create this sort of
the doer do a list opposite
and that almost creates sort of no no's
like case studies or feedback or and and
like how would you distinguish somebody
kind of be reminding you to stay
observant of your own processes of
observing and feedback you're solving a
problem again like boy is isn't isn't
feedback that as well know if I mean
that's why I'd talked about the the
environment the the it was creep we work
to particular create a particular
imagery field people have been through a
process and they are struggling to
understand to deepen learning to apply
it together and so they're all
experiencing themselves as being on a
learning path and part of this is
they're talking openly about the
frameworks that they're trying to bring
into their personal and professional
lives to to bring consciousness to it to
start to thin see it we've we introduced
you use I know it's a long time ago and
you had other things on your mind in the
therapy but little things like what's
the scope of our considering am I just
internally considering or am I actually
externally considering and what does
that mean by internally considering
everything relates to me mm-hmm
you know Daniel you're frowning I must
be doing something wrong
yeah now as opposed to Daniel you're
frowning can I figure out what it is
that's not working for you and I can
support you in now so that builds a
different relationship that has in it
both explicit and implicit too you know
and this was said in a joking way you
know it was not a chastising but it
became a little sort of a wake-up signal
as a signal as opposed to
sitting someone down and saying what I'm
seeing is that you're really
continuously you step back and you start
to solve problems and usually feedback
is followed by advice very hard for
people I'd watch this over and over
again to give feedback without then
giving advice because they have an
answer and what you do is you rob the a
the the person you're engaging with of
their own agency and that's the really
critical piece because that's that's
that's kind of the fundamental base is
without that personal agency the sense
of being able to bring will and and
strive to create something that that I
uniquely can contribute and it's
significant it's you know if I look at
equity for example one of the
definitions I love that came through in
this work on equity was equity is about
not not an equal starting ground so in a
functional material way but equal
opportunity to contribute what I
uniquely have to contribute and when you
start to think about it that way then
you're starting to say what is
preventing people from bringing their
unique contribution that's what we
should be working on and it's not a
material thing it's more a path it has
material implications but it's more a
path enabling up at that path of the
developing oneself is in and to one's
full potential and giving opportunities
to be able to think contribute that
potential to things that people care
about my sense is if we were really
focusing in on that I look at what's
happening that states and so many of the
people who are who see Trump is the kind
of a way to justify that they have
meaning they their value but it doesn't
it's an artificial exterior affirmation
as opposed to
seeing what's the real potential they
could bring providing infrastructural
opportunities and learning opportunities
that enable them to actually bring
develop and bring that potential is is a
world of difference and but we leave
we've created a void because we don't do
that we don't everybody is having
unlimited potential how do you see this
world like with all these like to some
extent I personally have come being
faced particularly last year with the
urgency of the climate crisis and and
trigger points coming in every hard and
fast and in political situations
worsening and and evil monsters
reappearing that one at four they'd like
like like all that fascists the
neo-fascist energy that is suddenly
popping up not just in the US but in
many other countries and I I almost kind
of got to a point of returning to being
rather than doing and appreciating what
is and really being with beauty and in
relationship and trusting that actually
that shift because it Repat ins a new
way of being in the world is it has
agency in itself and and is is actually
at the heart of it because if you try to
respond to the crisis and you frame
everything as a problem and like climate
change or ecosystems collapse rather
than pay attention to where these
symptoms come from you you might miss
the opportunity to respond appropriately
but there but but there's decentest
strange paradox between urgency and
radical slowing down between global
problems that could kill large parts of
life on earth and actually only ever
having one place and one time directed
which is local or by regional and now
how do you see all this work all this
capacity
building oldest like baby the sudden
surge of attention with regard to yes we
want regenerative futures we want to go
even beyond just being sustainable or
they make I agree that the framing of
not understanding sustainability as a
bridge that we have walked across yet
and and and belittling it in any way is
is the mistaken path but um how do we
build this capacity everywhere quick
yeah that's that's thinking functionally
in in functional scale when you say
everywhere so let's let's back away it's
a really I think it's a critical
question for a time and I was recently
in a really interesting dialogue with a
associate ins and somebody who's just
moved to a new position it's has some
quite a bit of influence and and looking
to how to use that that you remember are
the one of the little frameworks we use
a lot with law of three mm-hmm and you
have to sort of envision this you've got
one arrow is these three forces so one
force is usually what's the activating
or affirming force what gets something
started the other force that meets it at
the same plane is the restraining or
receptive force receiving force and it's
like if we live in what Gurjeet called a
two for third force blind world that's
it we just go back and forth and build
force or end up compromising down but in
the three forces there's a third force
that's the reconciling and that is the
one that if we can appreciate both of
the restraining and the activating force
hold that cognitive dissonance and
really appreciate what is the purpose
behind each
the the way this works is that third
force comes in he's like we create space
for reconciling worse
so in this dialogue with this friend it
was we were having this exact dialogue
and he was saying my god he said I hate
you know I hate it when they say they
only have 12 years but we only have two
oh yes but yep this is we really need to
move fast in its so I would say yes and
if we solve it and we are same so I
finally sent him a little log three and
I said so on when we have a Christ and
extinction crisis or an existential
crisis which is deals with we just may
destroy ourselves the earth probably
will last after but there's an
existential crisis that is getting more
and more imminent and real
we also are right now in the middle of
an ontological crisis who do we need to
be as humans on our planet earth and
what do we need to be working to bring
into being and so it's like those if we
solve one without the other if we take
that moment to just be and be in love
and in fields of caring and support and
we don't work on the other one then you
know we weren't wearing around to figure
out what our role is supposed to be so
they really we need to hold them both
and what that requires I think it's a
different way that's why working on our
own state as we work out in the world is
so fundamentally critical learning how
to do that and I've been I can't even
say the number of meetings over the last
four or five months that we've been in
planning various things and somebody
just says we've got to move faster I
mean we just we can't sit around and the
minute you go to that state you can no
long my experiences I can
no longer see the whole of what needs to
be worked on in this moment in this
place or it was in this to deal with
this particular situation so we loose we
narrow our consciousness in that moment
and we lose the ability to be effective
on the the crisis that we need to meet
in terms of out there in the world this
is fascinating because for me and on the
one hand the way you've just framed Fred
this is is like in many ways I feel this
very strongly in my own life it's this
dance between the even the tension
between how much work do I put into
weaving relationships at the biggest
scales of nested wholeness and and how
much attention do I put into the
immediate look like the local by
regional environment and in how much of
that is outlet and how much of that is
really inward and nourishing see but but
but the then you're already balancing
that so it really is it's it's the
process is one of harmony how do we
harmonize this you know harmony is not
all like it's a good harmony means every
single element has is playing its role
in a beautiful composition so you've got
the opportunity to work regionally to do
what essentially we did for in Regenesis
we spent years trying out developing
testing learning coming back and trying
out in on the ground and in if I thought
about the larger scale impact of that it
was you know especially in the early
years it wasn't that great until we
began to realize that we need to be
working at both levels and that was when
we set up the Institute as a way instead
in 2012 started moving towards that
aspect but you've got
the podcasts they do the the writing you
do so you're you've got an opportunity
to take that experiential hands-on
learning extract from it and put it into
language in ways that reach out and you
also have the opportunity that's why we
talk so much about nodal interventions
you are somebody who started early on
with an understanding of the importance
of the nested wholes and scales and
levels of life that's how life operates
and you you hit one level and deplete it
all the other levels eventually collapse
so all right you know that so you
whatever level you're working on as long
as you're holding that in your thinking
which means unique you can't collapse
into the urgency of now the panic that
was really so right but it like one day
it feels incredibly exhilarating and
exciting and and like a flow and meant
to be and everything and the other day I
feel like why am i torturing myself with
this tension of trying to hold all this
and John Bennett's wife there's some
some discussion about where this saying
came from but I think she is actually
the one she said that our being attracts
our life and we only get what we are
being is able to manage it's there's a
more elegant way of saying that but if
you're it that's because you've been
working on growing your state and and
what you are capable of handling and
managing and there's always going to be
that as you're on that growing edge when
you talk about the evolving edge it's
exactly it's not nobody promised that it
was going to be entirely comfortable the
entire but I just wanted to come back to
two things that bridge very beautifully
where we started and where we just got
to one of them was one year earlier were
saying that you were describing how you
white people off into how's the place
working on you our pattern Inuit I think
I can remember the exact and word you
use process because that's a pretty
important forms processes or what
transforms something so it's different
from just any activity well it's really
a transfer it's working to shift your
being at some level and the energies
you're experiencing that that create a
different state of being and that that
kind of reminded me a little bit of that
that flip and perspectives that makes
such a difference which is again an
indigenous insight where indigenous
cultures all over the world have been so
clear that they belong to the land
rather than the land could ever belong
to them so they they are the land the
expressions of the land they are being
processed constantly by the land their
language is a process that comes out of
the land and in in a similar way when
you were saying sharing this the sense
of collapsing not being able to hold the
whole when people go into this this
panic mode of of how we need to move
faster that this reminds me strongly of
the conversation I had with one of your
students John Johnny Freelander from
from New Zealand from the regenerative
practitioner cohorts there who as a as a
Maori we had this beautiful moment at
the at the Commonwealth meeting in
London where I was able to share some of
my frameworks and he would then mirror
them from his wisdom tradition
perspective and and one of these that
then was this concept of wow that they
have there of the of time that is again
Bennett speaks about this too with the
different hypotheses and so on the co
presence of the future and the past in
the presence and the potential of the
pattern of li patterning or creating the
future by reap a turning in the moment
it's a very Buddhist here as well
stored us not as moving towards the
future and any because in it comes also
this this sense that if everything is
fundamentally a dynamic nested wholeness
evolving coevolving mutuality then every
conversation has agency and there is no
such thing that the people who say we
have to move faster think that they're
not moving when they're having these
conversations and I in my I'm testing
this I might be wrong but I'm asking
would love your feedback on this my
increasingly I'm growing into this this
insight that no because it's all energy
in consciousness first that then shows
up at matter if we have these
conversations
we're actually happening it like we are
bringing for the world into being with
it has eight like this conversation has
agency right now yes and that's i again
here's it's just one of the things about
getting all this it kind of gives you a
few more years i don't believe it's a
lot more wisdom but a few more years of
experience to reflect back on efforts is
that yes that's true and it does not
excuse us from continuously working to
bring more intelligence and more
understanding to every interaction and
engagement into actually actualizing
something bringing committing to bring
something into being so i think that
it's like a both and that is true it's
incumbent on us we shift the energy
field that we is are working in when we
are able to bring and sustain that
nature of of state and consciousness and
it allows them people in that same field
to shift themselves and so but it's only
good as long as that energy field exists
when we step out of it
everybody has had this experience where
they've gone someplace they've had an
extraordinarily exhilarating experience
I mean one of the things that someone we
work with a lot that you know David
McConville and David did these
extraordinary experience all events and
what he realizes he began to get more
and more into this work was they were
ephemeral there were real real changes
occurred in people in that field but
it's ephemeral so that's why building
giving learning practices and frameworks
to shape how we see and think about the
world is and bringing the will and
discipline to do that is the only way we
can disrupt these deep patterns and be
conscious of when those patterns are
present I mean it's Krishnamurti one of
my favorite closest you may think you're
thinking your own thoughts you're not
you're thinking your cultures thoughts
the most the time we don't even know
that we're not conscious of it that
we're living out the patterns of the
larger culture that we've been brought
in and so I just want to make sure that
we don't I live through the hippy age
and then through the 70s
tea groups and and all of that and I
just saw so much of a you know drop out
and be for our children because the
world's so awful I can't do anything
about it I'm really worried that we
don't want to we want to be very clear
this is a rigorous practice that we're
called to bring to bring that
consciousness in the moment while we're
still working on this incredible
existential crisis but we're also
working on who humans can become and be
yeah that's and I you know it's just
having watched that through the through
the decades it's a is an incredibly
important up
Trinity right now for and when I think
of what we are being called to step up
to as a species a role that's that's
really different from even in indigenous
communities it's got it it's got to be
grounded back in that consciousness and
sense of always kinship that all is part
of life even you know we think of rocks
as inanimate but if you think in terms
of the cycle of life they were formed
out of energy into form they are
dissolving providing nutrients and
energy into future cycles if we start to
collectively see life in that see that
sense of multiple time in the moment
what a difference that would make in how
people make decisions in business and
politics in governance policies that's
my vision I think when moving towards
that and the jury is out but and you
don't change I mean I think when you say
I've sort of jumped on that we need to
give everybody the other thing I
experienced and this was what I gained
from working in large corporations part
of the sort of one of the fundamental
beliefs in this is is the power of
developing an energy field and how it
begins we're all we're always in energy
fields and they're shaping us whether
we're conscious of them or not
if we're in the middle of a mob we're
you know it's very clear that is but
it's wherever we are that's that sense
of being processed by a place we're
being processed by the energy field of
it and it one of the things that
everybody kept saying well who'd been
around for a long time in the network
when I joined was the the biggest hazard
is to feel like you have to touch
everybody in the corporation to make the
change hmm create the field in
place and others begin to be one drawn
to it or it begins to kitty carried out
by those who really can carry that field
with them and it was quite amazing to
see how and you look at this in terms of
major changes of the fall of the Soviet
Union there was not everybody got
touched for the field in the building
and you get a few lines of communication
at critical points and suddenly there's
a step function shift that nobody could
have predicted and I think we're at one
of those points now because there
there's I'm sure like you do I track you
know I have a lot of alerts on different
terms and so on just to kind of get a
sense of what's tracking in terms of
what people are writing about what
people are proposing and so on in regard
to regeneration and everything related
to it and you know unless we do
something really stupid like set off a
nuclear war which our current president
is capable of unfortunately I my sense
is that it's going to shift in ways we
have no idea yeah this I mean that this
reminds me of lost then I'd you enter
earlier was was the personal experience
of death and transcendence and likely of
understanding that death is part of life
really brought you into this work for me
that was one of the big insights when I
first started reading about the
generation like there it's actually the
little book that Ethan Rowland and
Gregory long recalled when they when
when there's a phrase like design for
your own death when you design a
regenerative Enterprise and I thought
that was just such a brilliant question
that our culture is blind to and and
actively avoids um and and and so
there's this the sense of also they like
Lea's remind of Brian Goodwin one of my
mentors true Mahakali to say to me
Daniel the secret of a fulfilling life
is to be ready at every moment to give
up who you are for what you could become
which is speaking very strongly to this
what what needs to die in me or bill was
sharing yesterday that that Regenesis
group has these these meetings where you
actually declare like you put yourself
to death in order to be reborn it's a
wonderful practice and as we wait to be
Janis generation yeah how do we really
need to invite people to embrace some of
the breakdown chaos and collapse that is
now all around us as as the unleashing
of the potential like even you can frame
it on in complex systems terms and a
complex dynamic system is most creative
at the edge of chaos when most of the
structures that no longer serve and
anachronistic have broken down and it's
fragile then but at the same time it has
all the potential for reorganization and
in bringing evolution and so I feel like
that's that that's where we at and and
yeah the ways we hold regeneration is go
right back to its you know I've seen a
lot of definitions renewal
Riis restoration and so on sort of as
the same thing regeneration is about
going back to the source of generation
what's what was the source of the birth
of something mm-hmm and that's that
essence that that and then in bring more
life to it so we're we're bringing more
life to what is so in a sense acai
giving up what we are is to discover who
we really are
in what's really our unique essence and
I this is if we don't have that as a
core fundamental in a census it's the
the cosmology is a part of it as how
that everything in the universe has its
own unique essence pattern this is bone
I mean this is really straight his
signings and it's an ancient belief
system but it bones work in terms of the
implicit order is the pattern of essence
that's constantly informing how things
get manifested in in the explicate order
but above that is the super to implicit
which is the sort of more unfettered
energies that inform that essence so can
we begin to go all have access to that
whole scale and bring it forward in
terms of how we're working and
understanding and the consciousness
we're trying to bring we'll see a lot
less of this trying to imprint on others
what we think is what progress and what
needs to happen we really deeply
appreciate that and strive to understand
and care about the the essence of each
of us holes I reach every city every
neighborhood every community that's a
living living the questions together
yeah
that's what I use as a sort of
catch catchphrase to run through my book
and it feel feels very akin to just
staying willing to yeah to manifest the
potential that lies in life as a like
Alfred North Whitehead the continuous
exploration of novelty but but with a
with a clap to the essence of what wants
to be expressed like you know we're
talking about indigenous cultures and
belief systems and ways the mind deloria
who I'm sure you know was just an
amazing person and one of the things he
has a book on where he talks about
education he and Daniel was like at and
the what he speaks to is that we you
need to always start education starting
with philosophy and we don't in the
Western where we start with our
philosophy or a belief system are
embedded and hidden so we start with
what needs to be done and and that's
where we run into these things so I
think it's part of this is in this
urgency of now of becoming conscious and
creating the the seedbed for coalescence
and and harmony is to start sharing more
more openly what is the source of our
beliefs about this why why do we believe
that what's the philosophy that's behind
what we're trying to do and the way
we're trying to do it right now and
those kinds of conversations having them
in those moments of we got to get moving
if we can take the discipline to say why
and and get to that fundamental belief
in philosophy level not in vast world
sense but right here right now in terms
of what we're arguing about in New
Mexico about how do we actually phase
out a coal plant and all the jobs that
are
I'm gonna be hit by a pork community so
we can work argue about the large issues
like global warming and so on or we can
start with what are we what we really
believe is right and good to do here
each of us and what's our philosophy
there Brett and can we start to see how
those can come together hmm we don't
have those kinds of conversations very
often I do feel that there is a shift
though that even in
[Music]
contexts like like government offices or
large corporations it is much more
possible to at least bring in this
conversation where they act on it is
another is another question but but
people are kind of seeing that they need
a new approach to need a fundamentally
different way of yeah no I agree I think
it is happening and we're Petaling like
mad to help support that happen and I
think it is what will enable us I mean I
this is where I think one of the
resonances with the powerful experience
of indigenous communities is when they
are intact you grow up in a whole
cosmology and ontology and then so in
taking care of kins
chips.the the river and the salmon and
so on you your culture the culture you
develop reinforces that and and gives
people the support and guidance without
laying down regulations and hard
policies you're continuously reinforcing
it from a being level out and so that
cultural piece is really critical and we
one of things we also work on people
being able to be more explicit and
conscious about what are the dimensions
of a culture that you really need to pay
attention to because they are signs of
what the underlying belief is that may
be long dead and frozen and no longer
accurate but it's still a domino you
know literally in the physical
structures out like in my in my
PhD work I was speaking a lot about how
design goes on designing and how when we
live in a city and we might put like
fiberglass and and like new wires and
and youth IT technology into the old
town of Edinburgh but as you walk
through that space you're still informed
by some design decisions and frameworks
that are 200-300 years old
that's why ontological design is such a
powerful way of thinking about that
because we don't we all the design
thinking and everything else is to get
the end product for the moment with
Vicki it goes on designing its world for
a long long time you're absolutely right
well this has been wonderful I'm
conscious that I don't want to take up
too much more of your time
um but yeah thank you so much for this
conversation and you know what I'll do
is I'll if it's okay with you I would
share this on YouTube and then run then
write a blog post about it to get it to
more people and in his beginning of a
conversation and assuming because I
tried to what I tried to focus on Daniel
and lift up was one dimension of our
work and I'm assuming that bill and
others that you will will pick up the
other dimensions because I don't you
know it's it's it can it can get really
kind of straight like I keep hearing
people talking about we do mental model
trainings we never use the word training
and we don't a mental model is somebody
else's explanation it's not a means to
be able to build one's own so I wanna if
we can just keep working away yeah no
I'm fine
that's exactly why I'm starting this
learning journey it's it's it's just a
wonderful way of learning myself and
then sharing the learning with other
people they will hear what we said
differently than we heard what we said
but but yeah I'm looking forward to
this this multifaceted perspective on
working the one thing that we maybe pick
up some other time is is this question
of now that there's such a buzz around
regeneration like I mentioned this
briefly with Bill yesterday as well like
how do you avoid because so many people
are now taking bits from whatever is out
there already repackaging it in a clever
way in the way that they've always done
that as consultants to just make
something buzz worthy and the new thing
and and then go out there and say sure I
can help you become a regenerative
cooperation and and on the one hand
maybe it's exciting that at least the
words out there and people are
interested in it and it's begin it's
opening a much wider wedge for the
conversation but how do we bring invite
people into a process of deepening that
even if it's just a small percentage of
those people who are now tuning into
this frequency realize that this is
actually committing to a long practice
of of
[Music]
self-reflection personal development
capacity development with the people you
work with in your community in your team
and and that then does the work in the
world it's not a quick of being showing
that it's a much more effective way to
work on things yes that's in it's it
might seem slower but in the end it's
it's faster it's there it's a good all
we've got to do that we did that's that
holding simultaneously realizing more
value more meaning and significance
while actualizing something that has
some far greater effect and
effectiveness and that are you in the
existence world we've got to do both yes
thank you sir and I'll just quickly stop
the recording just wanted to